<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Oral Presentation on David Vanegas-Alarcón</title>
    <link>https://davidvanegal.github.io/tags/oral-presentation/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Oral Presentation on David Vanegas-Alarcón</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>EN</language>
    <copyright>Registered trademark &amp;copy; 2020 Theme for Hugo by [Somrat](https://github.com/somratpro/somrat)</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 08 Sep 2025 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="https://davidvanegal.github.io/tags/oral-presentation/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Efecto del régimen de quema en escarabajos coprófagos en ambientes de pastoreo tropicales</title>
      <link>https://davidvanegal.github.io/blog/vanegasalarconetal20251/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 08 Sep 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://davidvanegal.github.io/blog/vanegasalarconetal20251/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Vanegas-Alarcón, D.A.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;&#xA;&lt;a href=&#34;https://orcid.org/0000-0002-4394-1711L&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://i.ibb.co/x5DD1Zp/ORCID.png&#34; alt=&#34;ORCID&#34; border=&#34;0&#34; width=&#34;2.5%&#34;&gt; [0000-0002-4394-1711]&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;González Tokman, D.&lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;&#xA;&lt;a href=&#34;https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7251-5773&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://i.ibb.co/x5DD1Zp/ORCID.png&#34; alt=&#34;ORCID&#34; border=&#34;0&#34; width=&#34;2.5%&#34;&gt; [0000-0001-7251-5773]&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;López Ortiz, S.&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;&#xA;&lt;a href=&#34;https://orcid.org/0000-0002-5202-3365&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://i.ibb.co/x5DD1Zp/ORCID.png&#34; alt=&#34;ORCID&#34; border=&#34;0&#34; width=&#34;2.5%&#34;&gt; [0000-0002-5202-3365]&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Arellano Gámez, L.&lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;&#xA;&lt;a href=&#34;https://orcid.org/0000-0001-6364-2447&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://i.ibb.co/x5DD1Zp/ORCID.png&#34; alt=&#34;ORCID&#34; border=&#34;0&#34; width=&#34;2.5%&#34;&gt; [0000-0001-6364-2447]&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h3&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;&#xA;&lt;ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Instituto de Ecología, A.C., Xalapa, Veracruz&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Colegio de Postgraduados, Campus Veracruz&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;h3 id=&#34;abstract&#34;&gt;Abstract&lt;/h3&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Introduction. The burning regime in pastures plays a fundamental role in maintaining biological diversity (Parr et al., 2014); however, this regime can negatively affect the diversity and functions of insects (Arellano and Castillo-Guevara, 2014). Objective. To analyze how burning regimes affect species diversity, functional groups, and dung removal by dung beetles in grazing environments in a dry forest landscape. Methods. Nine pitfall traps and four experimental units were arranged in 15 ranches managed with a burning regime (null, low, and high) and located in different grazing environments (monocultures of grasses, biodiverse pastures, and secondary vegetation). Results and discussion. The burning regime did not influence abundance, species richness, diversity, or dung removal by dung beetles. The species composition of dung beetles was influenced by the burning regime, with dung beetle assemblages differing in ranches with low or high burning regimes. Functionally, a negative effect of burning was observed in tunnellers and necrophages. Other functional groups did not show influence from the burning regime, remaining stable. This pattern could be due to changes in food availability, as well as species replacement in nearby sites. Conclusion. Changes in composition and functional groups influence the stability of dung beetle diversity, which could play a key role in the resilience of the grazing environments studied. It is essential to highlight that the timing of fire management in ranches and the adaptations of dung beetles are key factors for their survival in grazing environments affected by fire, such as silvopastoral systems.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Diversidad de escarabajos coprófagos (Scarabaeidae: Scarabaeinae) en tres tipos de coberturas vegetales en el municipio de Pijao-Quindío</title>
      <link>https://davidvanegal.github.io/blog/salazarecheverrietal2024/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 10 Jul 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://davidvanegal.github.io/blog/salazarecheverrietal2024/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Salazar Echeverri N.&lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;García Hernández A.L.&lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;&#xA;&lt;a href=&#34;https://orcid.org/0000-0003-1670-2018&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://i.ibb.co/x5DD1Zp/ORCID.png&#34; alt=&#34;ORCID&#34; border=&#34;0&#34; width=&#34;2.5%&#34;&gt; [0000-0003-1670-2018]&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Vanegas-Alarcón D.A.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;&#xA;&lt;a href=&#34;https://orcid.org/0000-0002-4394-1711&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://i.ibb.co/x5DD1Zp/ORCID.png&#34; alt=&#34;ORCID&#34; border=&#34;0&#34; width=&#34;2.5%&#34;&gt; [0000-0002-4394-1711]&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h3&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;&#xA;&lt;ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Grupo de Investigación Ecdysis, Centro de Estudios e Investigaciones en Biodiversidad y Biotecnología, Universidad del Quindío, Armenia, Quindío, Colombia&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Red de Ecoetología, Instituto de Ecología, Xalapa, México&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;h3 id=&#34;abstract&#34;&gt;Abstract&lt;/h3&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The main causes of loss of diversity and ecosystem services are linked to human activities, especially extensive agricultural and livestock activities. Colombia is a country that faces constant changes in land cover, especially due to livestock and extensive monoculture activities; therefore, it is important to carry out constant monitoring of its biodiversity. In this case, taxonomic diversity evaluates spatial and temporal patterns of communities, which helps us to understand the dynamics of assemblages at both regional and local levels. Thus, the objective of this research is to evaluate the taxonomic diversity of dung beetles (Scarabaeidae: Scarabaeinae) in three types of vegetation cover (banana crop, bamboo grove, and pre-montane forest) in the municipality of Pijao-Quindío. Three field trips were carried out in which seven pitfall traps were placed for each cover, baited with carrion bait and dung bait. Our results show that diversity values are higher in forest covers compared to the other covers. Regarding the species collected, among the genera that showed greater dominance we found &lt;em&gt;Dichotomius&lt;/em&gt; compared to other genera with low abundance values such as &lt;em&gt;Canthidium&lt;/em&gt;. In addition, alpha and beta diversity indices were evaluated, which showed a similar behavior, where vegetation covers with greater impact from different land uses have lower values in this type of indices.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Escarabajos coprófagos (Scarabaeidae: Scarabaeinae) de la Colección de Insectos de la Universidad del Quindío (CIUQ)</title>
      <link>https://davidvanegal.github.io/blog/robledopradaetal2023/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 26 Jul 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://davidvanegal.github.io/blog/robledopradaetal2023/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Robledo Prada M.&lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Vanegas-Alarcón D.A.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;&#xA;&lt;a href=&#34;https://orcid.org/0000-0002-4394-1711&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://i.ibb.co/x5DD1Zp/ORCID.png&#34; alt=&#34;ORCID&#34; border=&#34;0&#34; width=&#34;2.5%&#34;&gt; [0000-0002-4394-1711]&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;García Hernández A.L.&lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;&#xA;&lt;a href=&#34;https://orcid.org/0000-0003-1670-2018&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://i.ibb.co/x5DD1Zp/ORCID.png&#34; alt=&#34;ORCID&#34; border=&#34;0&#34; width=&#34;2.5%&#34;&gt; [0000-0003-1670-2018]&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Salazar Echeverri N.&lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Grupo de Investigación Ecdysis, Centro de Estudios e Investigaciones en Biodiversidad y Biotecnología, Universidad del Quindío, Armenia, Quindío, Colombia&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;h3 id=&#34;abstract&#34;&gt;Abstract&lt;/h3&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Biological collections are of great importance for preserving information over time, since they provide data about the collection, origin, and identification of species. In particular, the Insect Collection of the University of Quindío comprises around 40,000 specimens, of which a large part are dung beetles Scarabaeidae: Scarabaeinae, which are highly studied due to their ecological and functional importance for assessing the state of ecosystems. Thus, an inventory of the registered specimens was carried out by reviewing curatorial information, mounting, and taxonomic resolution. For this, the geographic and taxonomic representativeness of the records was determined, in addition to the pertinent photographic record. In this way, a representativeness of dung beetle species for Colombia of 13.7% was obtained, with a total of 42 species; likewise, for Quindío, 4,745 individuals were found with a geographic representativeness of 100%, with records in its 12 municipalities, of which the most representative was Quimbaya. For the Coffee Region, 42 species were recorded out of the 73 reported for the region. This work aims to provide a baseline of dung beetles of the subfamily Scarabaeinae present in the Insect Collection of the University of Quindío.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Comunidad de escarabajos coprófagos (Coleoptera: Scarabaeinae) y sus funciones ecológicas en tres tipos de coberturas vegetales en los andes colombianos</title>
      <link>https://davidvanegal.github.io/blog/ariasalvarezetal2019/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 28 Apr 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://davidvanegal.github.io/blog/ariasalvarezetal2019/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Arias-Álvarez G.A.&lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;&#xA;&lt;a href=&#34;https://orcid.org/0000-0001-9990-4525&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://i.ibb.co/x5DD1Zp/ORCID.png&#34; alt=&#34;ORCID&#34; border=&#34;0&#34; width=&#34;2.5%&#34;&gt; [0000-0001-9990-4525]&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;mailto:gustavoar2905@gmail.com&#34;&gt;gustavoar2905@gmail.com&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Vanegas-Alarcón D.A.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;&#xA;&lt;a href=&#34;https://orcid.org/0000-0002-4394-1711&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://i.ibb.co/x5DD1Zp/ORCID.png&#34; alt=&#34;ORCID&#34; border=&#34;0&#34; width=&#34;2.5%&#34;&gt; [0000-0002-4394-1711]&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;mailto:davidvaneal@gmail.com&#34;&gt;davidvaneal@gmail.com&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;García-Hernández A.L.&lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;&#xA;&lt;a href=&#34;https://orcid.org/0000-0003-1670-2018&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://i.ibb.co/x5DD1Zp/ORCID.png&#34; alt=&#34;ORCID&#34; border=&#34;0&#34; width=&#34;2.5%&#34;&gt; [0000-0003-1670-2018]&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;mailto:ikbolon84@gmail.com&#34;&gt;ikbolon84@gmail.com&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Lopera-Toro A.&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;&#xA;&lt;a href=&#34;https://orcid.org/0000-0001-5097-1655&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://i.ibb.co/x5DD1Zp/ORCID.png&#34; alt=&#34;ORCID&#34; border=&#34;0&#34; width=&#34;2.5%&#34;&gt; [0000-0001-5097-1655]&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;mailto:alejandro.lopera@gmail.com&#34;&gt;alejandro.lopera@gmail.com&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Andresen E.&lt;sup&gt;3&lt;/sup&gt;&#xA;&lt;a href=&#34;https://orcid.org/0000-0001-8957-4454&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://i.ibb.co/x5DD1Zp/ORCID.png&#34; alt=&#34;ORCID&#34; border=&#34;0&#34; width=&#34;2.5%&#34;&gt; [0000-0001-8957-4454]&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;mailto:andresen@iies.unam.mx&#34;&gt;andresen@iies.unam.mx&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Santos-Heredia M.C.&lt;sup&gt;4&lt;/sup&gt;&#xA;&lt;a href=&#34;https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7617-0581&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://i.ibb.co/x5DD1Zp/ORCID.png&#34; alt=&#34;ORCID&#34; border=&#34;0&#34; width=&#34;2.5%&#34;&gt; [0000-0001-7617-0581]&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;mailto:macasahe@gmail.com&#34;&gt;macasahe@gmail.com&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Grupo de Investigación Ecdysis, Centro de Estudios e Investigaciones en Biodiversidad y Biotecnología, Universidad del Quindío, Armenia, Quindío, Colombia&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Fundación Ecotrópico, Colombia&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Instituto de Investigaciones en Ecosistemas y Sustentabilidad, Universidad Nacional Autónoma de México, Morelia, México&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Facultad  de  Ciencias  Naturales,  Universidad  de  Santander,  Bucaramanga,  Colombia&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;h3 id=&#34;abstract&#34;&gt;Abstract&lt;/h3&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;We evaluated the effect of vegetation cover on dung beetle communities and their ecological functions, comparing and relating community attributes and functional performance across three vegetation types: secondary forest, mixed forest, and pasture, in the Montaña del Ocaso Reserve (Quimbaya, Quindío). Sampling was conducted using pitfall traps and functional stations, with three sites per vegetation type. Pitfall traps were arranged in the corners of a 50 × 50 m triangle, and functional stations were placed 2 m away, baited with a 7:3 mixture of pig dung and human feces. Experimental dung pats contained 50 beads of 4 mm, 20 of 8 mm, and 10 of 12 mm. After 48 h, dung removal was quantified, undispersed beads were collected, and excavated soil was dried and weighed. A total of 1,569 individuals were collected, representing 18 species and 10 genera. Diversity varied only in pastures, while secondary and mixed forests showed no differences. However, secondary forest exhibited higher functional performance: over 90% of beads were dispersed, dung and soil removal were substantial, and biomass and body length were greater compared to other covers. Results indicate that species composition does not differ among covers, but functional performance occurs in specific patches with suitable conditions. Moreover, insect attributes strongly influence the magnitude of ecological functions.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
