<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Experience on David Vanegas-Alarcón</title>
    <link>https://davidvanegal.github.io/portfolio/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Experience on David Vanegas-Alarcón</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>EN</language>
    <copyright>Registered trademark &amp;copy; 2020 Theme for Hugo by [Somrat](https://github.com/somratpro/somrat)</copyright>
    <atom:link href="https://davidvanegal.github.io/portfolio/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Asociación de Biólogos del Quindío</title>
      <link>https://davidvanegal.github.io/portfolio/asobioq2021/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://davidvanegal.github.io/portfolio/asobioq2021/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h4 id=&#34;functions-performed&#34;&gt;Functions performed&lt;/h4&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Management of the association&amp;rsquo;s financial resources through the bank account, ensuring the normal collection of ordinary and extraordinary accounts, as well as making the different payments that the Association must make and that are previously ordered by the president, the Board of Directors or the assembly&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Asociación de Biólogos del Quindío</title>
      <link>https://davidvanegal.github.io/portfolio/asobioq2022/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://davidvanegal.github.io/portfolio/asobioq2022/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h4 id=&#34;functions-performed&#34;&gt;Functions performed&lt;/h4&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Carry the legal representation of the Association, before public or private entities, in all the acts in which it intervenes, in addition to executing all the mandates of the Assembly and the Board of Directors&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Biotica Consultores - Universidad de Santander</title>
      <link>https://davidvanegal.github.io/portfolio/biotica2022/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://davidvanegal.github.io/portfolio/biotica2022/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;functions-performed&#34;&gt;Functions performed&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Develop a methodological proposal for the characterization of beetle communities. Characterize the beetle community in the field in the work windows established by prioritized biome within the framework of the main ecological structure project. Processing and analysis of the information recorded in the field that contains the calculation of indicators related to species diversity, abundance, functional groups and other statistical parameters that allow evaluating the completeness of the sampling, as well as the analysis of information related to records of importance for conservation, identification of attributes and ecological processes of the registered species that contribute to the analysis of ecosystem services and the model ecological structure.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Civil Service S.A.S.</title>
      <link>https://davidvanegal.github.io/portfolio/civilservice2023/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://davidvanegal.github.io/portfolio/civilservice2023/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;functions-performed&#34;&gt;Functions performed&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Collection of primary information in the field, following the guidelines given by the technical coordinator. Prepare the final coprophage monitoring report. Carry out the characterization of coprophages.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h3 id=&#34;summary&#34;&gt;Summary&lt;/h3&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Execute support activities to characterize beetles (Coleoptera: Scarabaeinae), under the project &amp;ldquo;Management service, subscription and monitoring of voluntary conservation agreements for compliance with environmental compensation and forced investment of no less than 1% required by environmental authorities to Ecopetrol in the municipalities of the upper Manacacías nucleus in the department of Meta”, signed between Civil Service and Ecopetrol.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Instituto de Recursos Biológicos Alexander von Humboldt</title>
      <link>https://davidvanegal.github.io/portfolio/iavh2021/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://davidvanegal.github.io/portfolio/iavh2021/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;functions-performed&#34;&gt;Functions performed&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Carry out sampling activities of beetle beetles and melolontid larvae. In addition to the taxonomic identification and physical curation of the specimens and their tissues and their registration in the Darwin Core file and in the migration file associated with biological collections.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h3 id=&#34;summary&#34;&gt;Summary&lt;/h3&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Under Agreement No. 21-095 signed with the National Hydrocarbons Agency - ANH, the survey of the general baseline of biodiversity and ecosystems was carried out for the area of interest of the Valle Medio del Magdalena, during the rainy season. tall. Biodiversity samplings of different biological groups were carried out, in this resource the results of dung beetles and Scarabaeidos larvae are presented. A total of 1642 biological records of dung beetles (Scarabaeinae subfamily) distributed in 21 species, 15 morphospecies and 15 genera were obtained. For Scarabaeidos larvae, 29 biological records were obtained distributed in 1 species, 8 morphospecies in 8 genera, belonging to the Dynastinae, Melolonthinae and Rutelinae subfamilies. For a total of 1671 records distributed in 22 species, 23 morphospecies and 23 genera. In each of the sampled points (40 in total) for the collection of dung beetles, 7 Pitfall-type traps baited with human excrement were installed, each trap separated by 50 meters. The specimens were collected at 24 and 48 hours. At 24 hours the traps were baited. For the search for Scarabaeidos larvae, 4 excavations of 1 square meter and 20 centimeters deep were carried out, in which the larvae were searched manually. The sampling effort was 280 Pitfall traps baited with human excrement and 160 hand searches.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Instituto de Recursos Biológicos Alexander von Humboldt</title>
      <link>https://davidvanegal.github.io/portfolio/iavh2022/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://davidvanegal.github.io/portfolio/iavh2022/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;functions-performed&#34;&gt;Functions performed&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Carry out sampling activities of beetle beetles and melolontid larvae. In addition to the taxonomic identification and physical curation of the specimens and their tissues and their registration in the Darwin Core file and in the migration file associated with biological collections.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h3 id=&#34;summary&#34;&gt;Summary&lt;/h3&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Under Agreement No. 21-095 signed with the National Hydrocarbons Agency - ANH, the survey of the general baseline of biodiversity and ecosystems was carried out for the area of interest of the Valle Medio del Magdalena, during the rainy season. tall. Biodiversity samplings of different biological groups were carried out, in this resource the results of dung beetles and Scarabaeidos larvae are presented. A total of 1642 biological records of dung beetles (Scarabaeinae subfamily) distributed in 21 species, 15 morphospecies and 15 genera were obtained. For Scarabaeidos larvae, 29 biological records were obtained distributed in 1 species, 8 morphospecies in 8 genera, belonging to the Dynastinae, Melolonthinae and Rutelinae subfamilies. For a total of 1671 records distributed in 22 species, 23 morphospecies and 23 genera. In each of the sampled points (40 in total) for the collection of dung beetles, 7 Pitfall-type traps baited with human excrement were installed, each trap separated by 50 meters. The specimens were collected at 24 and 48 hours. At 24 hours the traps were baited. For the search for Scarabaeidos larvae, 4 excavations of 1 square meter and 20 centimeters deep were carried out, in which the larvae were searched manually. The sampling effort was 280 Pitfall traps baited with human excrement and 160 hand searches.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Universidad de Santander</title>
      <link>https://davidvanegal.github.io/portfolio/udes2022/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://davidvanegal.github.io/portfolio/udes2022/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;functions-performed&#34;&gt;Functions performed&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Curatorship of the reference collection of beetles (Coleoptera: Scarabaeinae), Lepidoptera (butterflies) and Hymenoptera (Bees) to be delivered to Agrosavia under the guidelines of the collection of biological specimens. Development of the Darwin Core (DwC) standard allows the consolidation of data on biodiversity to share, use and refuse the information that must be delivered to the ANLA. Consolidation of the biodiversity database of the study area that will be used for statistical analysis.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
