<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Livestock on David Vanegas-Alarcón</title>
    <link>https://davidvanegal.github.io/tags/livestock/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Livestock on David Vanegas-Alarcón</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>EN</language>
    <copyright>Registered trademark &amp;copy; 2020 Theme for Hugo by [Somrat](https://github.com/somratpro/somrat)</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 09 Dec 2025 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="https://davidvanegal.github.io/tags/livestock/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Los escarabajos peloteros: una historia de fuego</title>
      <link>https://davidvanegal.github.io/blog/vanegasalarconetal2025/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 09 Dec 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://davidvanegal.github.io/blog/vanegasalarconetal2025/</guid>
      <description>&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.cronica.com.mx/academia/2025/09/12/los-escarabajos-peloteros-una-historia-de-fuego/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;&#xD;&#xA;La Crónica de Hoy&lt;/a&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;br&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;br&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Vanegas-Alarcón, D. A.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;&#xA;&lt;a href=&#34;https://orcid.org/0000-0002-4394-1711L&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://i.ibb.co/x5DD1Zp/ORCID.png&#34; alt=&#34;ORCID&#34; border=&#34;0&#34; width=&#34;2.5%&#34;&gt; [0000-0002-4394-1711]&lt;/a&gt;&#xA;, &lt;a href=&#34;mailto:davidvaneal@gmail.com&#34;&gt;davidvaneal@gmail.com&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Arellano Gámez, L.&lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;&#xA;&lt;a href=&#34;https://orcid.org/0000-0001-6364-2447&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://i.ibb.co/x5DD1Zp/ORCID.png&#34; alt=&#34;ORCID&#34; border=&#34;0&#34; width=&#34;2.5%&#34;&gt; [0000-0001-6364-2447]&lt;/a&gt;&#xA;, &lt;a href=&#34;mailto:lucrecia.arellano@inecol.mx&#34;&gt;lucrecia.arellano@inecol.mx&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Díaz-Rojas, A.&lt;sup&gt;3&lt;/sup&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;mailto:alfonso.diaz@inecol.edu.mx&#34;&gt;alfonso.diaz@inecol.edu.mx&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Red de Ecoetología, Instituto de Ecología A.C.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;h3 id=&#34;abstract&#34;&gt;Abstract&lt;/h3&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;OFire has historically been used as a management tool in cattle ranches of Veracruz, Mexico, to renew pastures and control parasites. However, repeated burning can negatively affect soil fertility and the diversity of soil fauna. This study evaluated the impact of fire use on dung beetle communities (Coleoptera: Scarabaeidae), key organisms in nutrient cycling and pasture maintenance. Dung beetles contribute to ecosystem functioning by removing dung, burying organic matter, and enhancing soil porosity and gas exchange. Results showed that recurrent fire events reduce the establishment of several dung beetle species, particularly necrophagous and tunneling taxa, while favoring species associated with cattle dung due to increased resource availability after burning. The decline of dung beetle diversity and functions may lead to pasture degradation, dung accumulation, and proliferation of flies and parasites. The findings highlight the need for planned and reduced fire use to conserve dung beetle assemblages and sustain ecosystem services in cattle landscapes of the region&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Efecto del régimen de quema en escarabajos coprófagos en ambientes de pastoreo tropicales</title>
      <link>https://davidvanegal.github.io/blog/vanegasalarconetal20251/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 08 Sep 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://davidvanegal.github.io/blog/vanegasalarconetal20251/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Vanegas-Alarcón, D.A.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;&#xA;&lt;a href=&#34;https://orcid.org/0000-0002-4394-1711L&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://i.ibb.co/x5DD1Zp/ORCID.png&#34; alt=&#34;ORCID&#34; border=&#34;0&#34; width=&#34;2.5%&#34;&gt; [0000-0002-4394-1711]&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;González Tokman, D.&lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;&#xA;&lt;a href=&#34;https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7251-5773&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://i.ibb.co/x5DD1Zp/ORCID.png&#34; alt=&#34;ORCID&#34; border=&#34;0&#34; width=&#34;2.5%&#34;&gt; [0000-0001-7251-5773]&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;López Ortiz, S.&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;&#xA;&lt;a href=&#34;https://orcid.org/0000-0002-5202-3365&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://i.ibb.co/x5DD1Zp/ORCID.png&#34; alt=&#34;ORCID&#34; border=&#34;0&#34; width=&#34;2.5%&#34;&gt; [0000-0002-5202-3365]&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Arellano Gámez, L.&lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;&#xA;&lt;a href=&#34;https://orcid.org/0000-0001-6364-2447&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://i.ibb.co/x5DD1Zp/ORCID.png&#34; alt=&#34;ORCID&#34; border=&#34;0&#34; width=&#34;2.5%&#34;&gt; [0000-0001-6364-2447]&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h3&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;&#xA;&lt;ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Instituto de Ecología, A.C., Xalapa, Veracruz&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Colegio de Postgraduados, Campus Veracruz&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;h3 id=&#34;abstract&#34;&gt;Abstract&lt;/h3&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Introduction. The burning regime in pastures plays a fundamental role in maintaining biological diversity (Parr et al., 2014); however, this regime can negatively affect the diversity and functions of insects (Arellano and Castillo-Guevara, 2014). Objective. To analyze how burning regimes affect species diversity, functional groups, and dung removal by dung beetles in grazing environments in a dry forest landscape. Methods. Nine pitfall traps and four experimental units were arranged in 15 ranches managed with a burning regime (null, low, and high) and located in different grazing environments (monocultures of grasses, biodiverse pastures, and secondary vegetation). Results and discussion. The burning regime did not influence abundance, species richness, diversity, or dung removal by dung beetles. The species composition of dung beetles was influenced by the burning regime, with dung beetle assemblages differing in ranches with low or high burning regimes. Functionally, a negative effect of burning was observed in tunnellers and necrophages. Other functional groups did not show influence from the burning regime, remaining stable. This pattern could be due to changes in food availability, as well as species replacement in nearby sites. Conclusion. Changes in composition and functional groups influence the stability of dung beetle diversity, which could play a key role in the resilience of the grazing environments studied. It is essential to highlight that the timing of fire management in ranches and the adaptations of dung beetles are key factors for their survival in grazing environments affected by fire, such as silvopastoral systems.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
